American Psychosomatic Society Records Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
American Psychosomatic Society Records
1938 - 1991
This collection the records of the American Psychosomatic Society. The collection has 8 series: Psychosomatic Medicine Journal, Annual Meetings, Governance, Research Activities, Membership, Financial Operations, Printed Material, and Administrative Files.
91.15 linear feet (213 boxes)
American Psychosomatic Society
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1995.0001
Gift of the American Psychosomatic Society, 1995.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
In her 1994 publication Mind, Body, and Medicine: A History of the American Psychosomatic Society, author Dorothy Levenson presents a decade by decade history of the American Psychosomatic Society. The section below, based in part upon information in Levenson's book, summarizes early events in the establishment of the journal of "Psychosomatic Medicine" and later, the American Psychosomatic Society, and a 1994 brochure provides up-to-date information about the Society. The American Psychosomatic Society grew out of a desire among academicians, practitioners, and foundations to link developments in psychology and psychiatry to internal medicine, physiology, and other disciplines. In the United States, efforts to establish an organ that could address these developments date to the 1930s. In 1936, Kate Macy Ladd, philanthropist and founder of the Josiah Macy, Jr. Foundation, directed her foundation to provide financial support for the fledgling field of psychosomatic investigation. An initial project to assemble a bibliography of "psychosomatic" medical literature, examining the relationship of religion to health, was undertaken by the New York Academy of Medicine's Joint Committee on Religion and Medicine. The Committee, headed by Dr. Helen Flanders Dunbar, published a first volume in 1935 titled, "Emotions and Bodily Changes: A Survey of the Literature on Psychosomatic Interrelationships." According to R.C. Powell who devoted a PhD thesis to Dunbar, this work “quite literally launched the `American psychosomatic movement.” With further financial assistance from the Macy Foundation, a Committee on Problems of Neurotic Behavior, under the direction of the National Research Council's Division of Anthropology and Psychology, soon began publication of a journal entitled "Psychosomatic Medicine." Its goal was to encourage collaboration among the medical specialties, psychology, and the social sciences. Financed by the Macy Foundation, sponsored by the National Research Council, managed by an Editorial Board, and overseen by an Advisory Board of prominent doctors and scholars representing a range of disciplines, the Journal had complex beginnings. Its first four issues appeared in 1939 under the editorship of Dr. Dunbar. By 1942, in response to the Second World War, interest and research in the new field had expanded rapidly. Other than the Journal, however, no forum was available for the exchange of ideas and information. In response, in December of 1942, the Journal's Advisory Board voted into existence the "American Society for Research in Psychosomatic Problems." By 1943, subscriptions to the Journal had more than doubled, and in 1944, the National Research Council relinquished their control of the Journal to the new Society. In 1948, the Society changed its name to become the "American Psychosomatic Society."
American Psychosomatic Society; Josiah Macy, Jr. Foundation; Dunbar, Helen Flanders, 1902-1959; American Society for Research in Psychosomatic Problems; George Banta Publishing Company; National Research Council (U.S.). Division of Anthropology and Psychology; United States. War Production Board; Aldrich, C. Anderson (Charles Anderson), 1888-1949; Alexander, Franz, 1891-1964; Atchley, Dana W. (Dana Winslow), 1892-1982; Cobb, Stanley, 1887-1968; Hoskins, R. G. (Roy Graham), 1880-1964; Liddell, H. S. (Howard Scott), 1895-; Powers, Grover Francis, 1887-1968; Whitehorn, John C. (John Clare), 1894-1973; Diethelm, Oskar, 1897-; Meyer, Adolf, 1866-1950; Miles, Walter R. (Walter Richard), 1885-1978; Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978; Binger, Carl (Carl Alfred Lanning), 1889-1976; Reiser, Morton F., 1919-; Weiner, Herbert E., 1921-; Hawkins, David R., 1927-; Shapiro, Alvin P. (Alvin Philip), 1920-; Abram, Harry S.; National Research Council (U.S.). Committee on Problems of Neurotic Behavior; Saul, Leon J. (Leon Joseph), 1901-1983; Lacey, John I.; Arlow, Jacob A.; Masserman, Jules H. (Jules Homan), 1905-1994
This is largely a collection of administrative files created by the Society, the vast majority of which were systematically filed by Joan Erpf, secretary and later executive assistant for the Society from as early as 1946 until her death in the mid 1980s. The majority of records document the administrative procedures by which the Society carried out its major functions, which traditionally have included membership operations, the publication of the journal, and the staging of an annual meeting.
There is documentation for the founding and early years of the Journal and Society; conference proceedings on topics in psychosomatic medicine discussed by the Society's research committees in the 1940s (eg., physiological mechanisms and animal experimentation, cutaneous and allied diseases, relation of mental illness to bodily ill health); correspondence and manuscript reviews reflecting procedures used by the Journal over several decades; early hand-written membership applications (for both accepted and rejected applicants) including those of founding members of the Society accompanied by membership recommendations; and correspondence and advertising proofs reflecting publishing, printing, and advertising procedures employed by the Journal. Early manuscript reviews written before the establishment of a formal review process are located in Record Group 1 in the Editors subgroup, often within the text of correspondence between editors. In the Journal's first years, its business management (including printing and advertising) was divided between the National Research Council and George Banta Publishing Co. After the 1940s, the Journal alternated between different companies for its printing and publishing needs, sometimes using a single company for both.
Materials most commonly found in the collection include carbon copy and original administrative correspondence among Society officers, editors, members, authors, publishers, and others; committee minutes and conference proceedings; election materials such as ballots, and slates; financial records such as invoices and accountant's reports; abstracts of articles and reviews or critiques of manuscripts submitted to the Journal; and printed materials, such as brochures or bulletins. Indices (e.g., for minutes, reports, and publications) have not been located in the collection. With a few exceptions, the collection does not contain manuscripts for articles or monographs, because, upon reviewing such materials, the Society returned them to authors. Likewise, the collection does not contain published monographs or print copies of the Journal. The Journal is available on microfilm. All records received from the Society have been retained, with the exception of duplicate materials. Following the request of the Library, even among records of a routine administrative nature (such as invoices, letters of transmittal, standard requests for information), weeding was not performed.
- Psychosomatic Medicine Journal
  - Advertising, Publishing, and Printing, 1938 - 1965; Folders are arranged by name of printer, publisher, or advertiser (e.g., "Hoeber, Inc.) or by subjects designated by the Society (e.g., "Advertising and Promotion"). Files include routine administrative correspondence and contracts carried out between the Society and advertisers, printers, and publishers and proofs for advertisements in the Journal, invoices, and financial records. Box four contains topical correspondence about paper allotments imposed on the Society by the US War Production Board in 1944, journal circulation and subscriptions, and permissions to quote.
    - George Banta Publishing Company, 1938 - 1942; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Waverly Press, 1943 - 1944 (Box 1)
    - Williams and Wilkins Co., 1941 - 1944; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Williams and Wilkins Co. transfer of Journal to Society, 1943 - 1944 (Box 1)
    - Lord Baltimore Press, 1944 - 1947 (Box 1)
    - Paul B. Hoeber Inc. (publisher) correspondence, memos, contract, minutes, 1946 - 1956; 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Paul B. Hoeber Inc. correspondence, 1959 - 1961; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Hoeber Medical Division (Harper and Row Publishers) correspondence, rate card, contract, 1962 - 1969; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Medical Department (Harper and Row Publishers) correspondence, minutes, 1970 - 1973 (Box 2)
    - Kraus Reprint Corp. contract, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Bobbs-Merrill Co. (reprints) correspondence, 1962 - 1973 (Box 2)
    - Charles Morchand (advertiser) memos, correspondence, contract, 1955 - 1956 (Box 2)
    - American Elsevier Publishing Co. contract, correspondence, 1972 - 1976 (Box 2)
    - Elsevier North Holland publishers correspondence, contract, 1976 - 1978 (Box 2)
    - Advertising Correspondence and Proofs (Charles Morchand Co.), 1953 - 1959; 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Proposals, Other Publishers, 1951 - 1952 (Box 4)
    - Proposals, Other Publishers, 1971 (Box 4)
    - "Promotions and Advertising" files, correspondence, 1939 - 1946; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Circulation Figures, 1939 - 1946 (Box 4)
    - Subscription List by Institution, 1944 (Box 4)
    - "Journal Advertising - Subscriptions" correspondence and subscription lists, 1952 (Box 4)
    - Printing Estimates, 1944 - 1946 (Box 4)
    - War Production Board Paper Allotment, 1944 - 1945 (Box 4)
    - Army-Navy Medical Procurement Office, NYC correspondence, subscription agreements, 1946 (Box 4)
    - Permission to Quote, 1946 - 1979; 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Committees, 1944 - 1980; Arranged alphabetically by committee title. The above committees were formed to address a variety of matters relating to the publication of the Journal. Includes administrative correspondence between committee members, memoranda to committee members, excerpts from committee minutes, "curriculum vitae" for candidates under consideration for editorial appointments, and candidates' statements of intent.
    - Abstracts Committee, 1944 - 1954 (Box 5)
    - Monographs Committee, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Committee to Appoint Editor-in-Chief, 1960 - 1961 (Box 5)
    - Editorial Executive Committee, 1963 - 1964 (Box 5)
    - Committee to Appoint Editor-in-Chief, Correspondence Statements of Intent Curriculum Vitae, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Committee to Appoint Editor-in-Chief, Correspondence Statements of Intent Curriculum Vitae, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Ad Hoc Committee for Journal Name Change, 1977 - 1978 (Box 5)
    - Search Committee to Appoint Editor-in-Chief Correspondence "Curriculum Vitae", Undated (Box 5)
  - Editorial Board, 1937 - 1986
    - Editorial Board Members, 1937 - 1946; Arranged alphabetically by name of board member. This subgroup includes carbon copy and original correspondence, including telegrams, to and from editorial board members. It documents concerns voiced by editors about the direction and administration of both the Journal and the Society during their early phases. Topics discussed include nominations, meeting program planning and scheduling, and materials for publication for early issues of the Journal. The first members of the editorial board were primarily the first authors of articles for the Journal. NOTE: The collection does not include the manuscripts or publications discussed in the correspondence. Files for the following board members are included in this series: Dr. C. Anderson Aldrich, Dr. Franz Alexander, Dr. Dana Atchley, Dr. Stanley Cobb, Dr. Roy Hoskins, Dr. Clark Hall, Dr. Howard Liddell, Dr. Grover Powers, and Dr. John Whitehorn.
      - Dr. C. Anderson Aldrich, 1943 - 1946 (Box 6)
      - Dr. Franz Alexander, 1937 - 1941; 4 folders (Box 6)
      - Dr. Franz Alexander, 1942 - 1946; 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Dr. Dana Atchley, 1937 - 1942 (Box 6)
      - Dr. Stanley Cobb, 1937 - 1942; 4 folders (Box 6)
      - Dr. Roy Hoskins, 1937 - 1946; 4 folders (Box 7)
      - Dr. Clark Hull, 1937 - 1942 (Box 7)
      - Dr. Howard Lindell, 1938 - 1946; 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Dr. Grover Powers, 1938 - 1943 (Box 7)
      - Dr. John Whitehorn, 1939 - 1946 (Box 7)
    - Meetings and Memoranda, 1957 - 1980; Arranged chronologically. Includes administrative memoranda to the Editorial Board from the Society's executive assistant, editor's reports, and meeting minutes of the Editorial Board. SEE: Record Group 1, Editors subgroup, for pre-1957 memoranda to the Board.
      - 1957-1961, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - 1962-1967, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - 1968-1972, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - 1973, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - 1974-1976, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - 1980, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Subject Files, 1953 - 1986; Arranged alphabetically by subject. Includes editors' administrative correspondence discussing supplements to the Journal, letters to the editor, a name change for the Journal, publication and funding for a cumulative index, and special issues to devoted various topics or individuals (e.g., adrenal cortex, 15th anniversary, Dr. Freud, Dr. Binger). NOTE: In most cases, this subgroup does not contain the letters to the editor or supplementary issues of the Journal, only correspondence about the letters and issues.
      - Published Letters to the Editor and Correspondence, 1958 - 1986; 4 folders (Box 10)
      - Enlarged Issue and Journal Name Change Correspondence, 1967; 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Cumulative Index Correspondence, 1958 - 1960; 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Special Issues Correspondence, Adrenal Cortex Issue, 1953 (Box 10)
      - Special Issues Correspondence, NP Issue, 1954 (Box 10)
      - Special Issues Correspondence, 15th Anniversary Issue, 1954 (Box 10)
      - Special Issues Correspondence, Freud Issue, 1956 (Box 10)
      - Special Issues Correspondence, Cannon Issue, 1957 (Box 10)
      - Special Issues Correspondence, Dr. Binger Issue, 1961 - 1962; 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Supplement Correspondence, Timberline Conference Proceedings, 1963 - 1967 (Box 11)
      - Supplement Correspondence, Alcohol, Mendelson, 1966 (Box 11)
      - Supplement Correspondence, Organization of Psychoendocrine Mechanisms, 1968 (Box 11)
      - "Editorial Notes" and "News of the Society", 1952 - 1970; 3 folders (Box 11)
      - "Journal - Education Section", 1975 (Box 11)
      - Communications in Behavioral Biology on publication of abstracts and reviews of the APS publications, 1967 - 1973 (Box 11)
      - Journal of Human Stress, 1975 - 1976 (Box 11)
  - Editors, 1937 - 1984; Arranged by editorial title and name of editor. Includes carbon copy and original correspondence and reports written to or by editors of the Journal. Highlights include the files of Dr. Helen Flanders Dunbar, the first managing editor of the Journal, containing 1) correspondence by and to her from members of the Journal's Advisory Board (correspondence with Oskar Diethelm, Adolf Meyer and other prominent individuals from a variety of disciplines is contained here) regarding administrative matters or critiquing or discussing articles or monographs to be published by the Journal, 2) reports by the Journal's sponsor, the Committee on Problems of Neurotic Behavior of the National Research Council, 3) her correspondence to and from Dr. Walter Miles, Chairman of the Committee, discussing business management and publication of the Journal, and 4) correspondence about the first issue of the Journal. By the 1930s, Dr. Dunbar discontinued use of her first name "Helen," assuming the name" Dr. Flanders Dunbar." Letters addressed to her as "Dear Sir" appear throughout the collection. Editor Dr. Binger's "General Correspondence - M" files include brief (but humorous) correspondence from Margaret Mead. Files for the following editors are found in this series: Managing Editors Dr. Flanders Dunbar (1937-1944) and Ruth Potter (1945-1947); Editors-in-Chief Dr. Carl Binger (1947-1962), Dr. Morton Reiser (1962-1966), and Dr. Herbert Weiner (1972-1980); Abstracts Editors Dr. David Hawkins (1958-1969), Dr. Alvin Shapiro (1964), Dr. Harry Abram (1969-1984), and Dr. Leon Saul (1943-1958); Book Review Editor Dr. Stanley Cobb (1947-1952); Review Editor (Technical Contribution Section) Dr. John I. Lacey (1962-1965).
    - Managing Editors, 1937 - 1946
      - "Dr. Dunbar's file for First Issue of Journal", 1937 - 1938 (Box 12)
      - Dr. Flanders Dunbar National Research Council, Dr. Walter Miles Correspondence, 1938 - 1944; 3 folders (Box 12)
      - Dr. Flanders Dunbar National Research Council, Dr. Leonard Carmichad Correspondence, 1939 - 1944 (Box 12)
      - Dr. Flanders Dunbar Advisory Board Correspondence, A through F, 1938 - 1943 (Box 12)
      - Dr. Flanders Dunbar Advisory Board Correspondence, Oskar Diethelm, 1939 - 1941 (Box 12)
      - Dr. Flanders Dunbar Advisory Board Correspondence, G through K, 1938 - 1942 (Box 12)
      - Dr. Flanders Dunbar Advisory Board Correspondence, L through R, 1938 - 1942 (Box 12)
      - Dr. Flanders Dunbar Advisory Board Correspondence, S, 1938 - 1942 (Box 12)
      - Dr. Flanders Dunbar Advisory Board Correspondence, T through Z, 1938 - 1942 (Box 12)
      - Dr. Flanders Dunbar Advisory Board Correspondence, Form Letters sent to Advisory Board, 1944 (Box 12)
      - Ruth Potter (European Trip) Correspondence, 1946 (Box 12)
    - Editor-in-Chief, 1947 - 1981
      - Dr. Carl Binger General Correspondence A-B, 1947 - 1962; 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Dr. Carl Binger General Correspondence C-H, 1947 - 1962; 5 folders (Box 13)
      - Dr. Carl Binger General Correspondence I-L, 1947 - 1962 (Box 13)
      - Dr. Carl Binger General Correspondence M-R (includes Margaret Mead), 1947 - 1962; 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Dr. Carl Binger General Correspondence S, 1947 - 1962; 3 folders (Box 14)
      - Dr. Carl Binger General Correspondence T-Z, 1947 - 1962; 3 folders (Box 14)
      - Dr. Carl Binger Correspondence Regarding "Editorial Note" to Editorial Board, Council Meeting Minutes, 1947 (Box 14)
      - Dr. Carl Binger Editor-in-Chief Reports, Editorial Board Minutes, 1947 - 1955 (Box 14)
      - Dr. Carl Binger Correspondence and Editor-in-Chief's Reports, 1960 - 1962 (Box 14)
      - Dr. Carl Binger Correspondence Acceptance of Appointments to Advisory Board, 1947 - 1949 (Box 14)
      - Dr. Carl Binger Correspondence Acceptance of Appointments to Associate Editor, 1949 - 1952 (Box 14)
      - Dr. Carl Binger Correspondence, Appointments and Acceptances of Associate Editors, Undated; 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Dr. Carl Binger Correspondence, Appointments and Retirements from Editorial Board, 1949 - 1952; 3 folders (Box 15)
      - Dr. Carl Binger Correspondence, Appointments and Retirements from Editorial Board, 1952 - 1962; 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Dr. Carl Binger Correspondence, Invitations and Appointments to Associate Editor, 1957; 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Dr. Carl Binger Correspondence Regarding Journal Cover and Seal, 1947 - 1952 (Box 15)
      - Sketches and Mark-ups for Emblem and Seal, 1947 - 1952 (Box 15)
      - Dr. Carl Binger Correspondence, Appointment of Dr. Saul to Deputy Editor, 1957 (Box 15)
      - Dr. Morton Reiser General Correspondence, 1962 - 1966; 3 folders (Box 16)
      - Dr. Morton Reiser General Correspondence, 1967 - 1968 (Box 16)
      - Dr. Morton Reiser General Correspondence, 1969 - 1971 (Box 16)
      - Dr. Morton Reiser Correspondence, Invitations and Appointments to Editorial Board, 1962; 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Dr. Morton Reiser Correspondence, Memoranda and Reports, Undated; 3 folders (Box 16)
      - Dr. Morton Reiser Correspondence, Invitations and Appointments to Editorial Board, 1968 - 1970 (Box 16)
      - Dr. Morton Reiser Correspondence, Invitations and Appointments to Editorial Board, 1971 - 1972 (Box 16)
      - Dr. Herbert Weiner Correspondence and Memoranda to Editorial Board, 1972 - 1975; 4 folders (Box 17)
      - Dr. Herbert Weiner General Correspondence M, 1972 - 1975; 3 folders (Box 17)
      - Dr. Herbert Weiner General Correspondence, 1976 (Box 17)
      - Dr. Herbert Weiner General Correspondence, 1980 - 1981 (Box 17)
      - Dr. Herbert Weiner Correspondence, Invitations, and Appointments to Editorial Board, 1976 (Box 17)
      - Dr. Herbert Weiner Correspondence, Invitations, and Appointments to Editorial Board, 1976 - 1980 (Box 17)
    - Abstracts Editors, 1943 - 1984
      - Dr. David Hawkins Correspondence, 1958 - 1959 (Box 18)
      - Dr. David Hawkins Correspondence, 1960 (Box 18)
      - Dr. David Hawkins Correspondence, 1961 - 1962 (Box 18)
      - Dr. David Hawkins Correspondence, 1963 (Box 18)
      - Dr. Alvin Shapiro Correspondence, 1964 (Box 18)
      - Dr. David Hawkins Correspondence, 1965 (Box 18)
      - Dr. David Hawkins and Joan Erpf Correspondence, 1965 - 1969 (Box 18)
      - Dr. Harry Abram Correspondence, 1969 - 1971 (Box 18)
      - Dr. Harry Abram and Joan Erpf Correspondence, 1971 - 1984 (Box 18)
      - Dr. Leon Saul Correspondence, 1943 - 1950 (Box 19)
      - Dr. Leon Saul Correspondence, 1950 - 1951 (Box 19)
      - Dr. Leon Saul Correspondence, 1952 (Box 19)
      - Dr. Leon Saul Correspondence, 1953 (Box 19)
      - Dr. Leon Saul Correspondence, 1954 (Box 19)
      - Dr. Leon Saul Rejected Abstracts A, 1946 - 1955 (Box 19)
      - Dr. Leon Saul "General Correspondence", 1954 - 1955 (Box 19)
      - Dr. Leon Saul "General Correspondence", 1956 (Box 19)
      - Dr. Leon Saul "General Correspondence", 1957 - 1958 (Box 19)
    - Book Review Editors, 1945 - 1965
      - Martin Grotjahn and Managing Editor Ruth Potter, 1945 - 1947 (Box 20)
      - Dr. Stanley Cobb Correspondence, 1947 (Box 20)
      - Dr. Stanley Cobb Correspondence, 1948 (Box 20)
      - Dr. Stanley Cobb Correspondence, 1949 (Box 20)
      - Dr. Stanley Cobb Correspondence, 1950; 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Dr. Stanley Cobb Correspondence, 1951; 3 folders (Box 20)
      - Dr. Stanley Cobb Correspondence, 1952; 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Review Editor (Technical Contributions Section) Dr. John I. Lacey Correspondence, 1962 - 1965 (Box 20)
    - Acting and Transitional Editors, 1963 - 1982
      - Adrian M. Ostfeld Correspondence, 1963 - 1967 (Box 21)
      - Peter H. Knapp Correspondence, 1969 (Box 21)
      - Editor-in-Chief Transition Correspondence, 1972 (Box 21)
      - Editorial Board Transition Correspondence, 1977 (Box 21)
      - Dr. William Greene Correspondence, 1980 (Box 21)
      - Transition (A. Weiner to D. Oken) Correspondence, 1981 - 1982 (Box 21)